# 大家好 很久都沒吃過肉啦
Hi everyone! We haven't had any meat for a long time.
# 拿個魚竿來 釣點魚回去烤
So I come with a fishing pole, to catch some fish and grill them.
# 不知道能不能釣得到 (註︰這裡如果用"I don't know if..."或"I wonder.."感覺會帶點否定，和他原意不太配合)
Let's see if we can catch any
# 魚都可以看的到 好多哇
I can see the fish already. There are a lot!
# 哎喲
Ayo!
# 都不咬鈎的
They don't bite the hook at all.
# 釣那麼久都還不咬鈎
I've been here for such a long time but no fish have ever bitten the hook.
# 你看 那麼菜葉子就是給個魚吃的
Look! Those veggie leaves are food for the fish.
# 下面還有鴨子哦
There are ducks down there too.
# 用魚鈎來鈎鴨子應該很好釣 一下子就可以釣得到
I think catching the ducks with the hook wouldn't take too much effort. A single pull is all what's needed.
# 可能姿勢不對哦
Is it because of my posture?
# 釣不到的
I can't catch any.
# 唉
Ey?
# 哦
Oh?
# 這個角落沒有魚的 我去那邊
There aren't any fish at this corner. I'm going to that,
# 那邊釣 (註︰「釣」字不譯了，譯了反而更怪，但上句刪去"side"字以保留不完整的感覺)
that side.
# 一條魚都沒釣到 魚鈎都不咬的
Not even a single fish. They didn't bite the hook at all.
# 下次我叫兄弟搞一隻鴨子來吃
Next time I'll ask my buddy to get me a duck.
# 下面那個鴨子
I mean the ducks down there.
# 幾天後
A few days later
# 上次我去兄弟釣魚
Last time we went fishing at my buddy's place.
# 一條都沒有釣到
But we couldn't catch any.
# 今天他送了一條給我
Today, he gave me a fish.
# 應該有2斤多
It should be at least a kilogram.
# 我們去把它給 給處理一下
Let's have it, have it processed,
# 去河邊
at the riverside.
# 割點花出來哦
Let slice it a few times.
# 這把刀不是很利
This knife is not really that sharp.
# 拿的家里的水果刀 菜刀又不見了
This is my cutting knife. The kitchen knife is again nowhere to be found.
# 這邊也是
This side too.
# 好啦
Alright!
# 等一下我們就放點
Then we'll marinate it,
# 放點鹽跟生薑那些 先腌一下
marinate it first with some salt, and ginger and whatever.
# 等一下用鍚紙裏起來
Then, wrap it up with aluminium foil,
# 烤一下
and grill it.
# 可以
Okay!
# 這袋子 把它裝起 (註︰我聽到他是說「把它裝"肥"去」)
The bag, put it in the bag.
# 我先回去啦
Let me go back first.
# 先把這個鍚紙
Let's get the foil,
# 把這個釣紙搞起來 (註︰「搞起來」是甚麼意思？)
get the foil ready first.
# 把這個魚放到這裡
And then put the fish here.
# 放點鹽 放到傷口上
Put some salt, and rub it into the wound.
# 可以啦
Should be alright now
# 這個是醬油 (註︰其實這應該不是醬油，即不是用大豆釀制的，這應該是用小麥釀制的鮮露，但我不管他了，他怎說我怎譯)
This is soy sauce.
# 再加點這個 這個是油哦
And also some, well, this is oil,
# 是植物油
veggie oil.
# 夠啦 不要那麼多
Enough. We don't need that much.
# 這是葱
This is spring onion.
# 搞點葱
Put some spring onion.
# 塞它肚子上去
Stuff it into the belly.
# 咬點這個葱
Have a bite of the spring onion.
Having a bite of the spring onion,
# 煮起來的時候就沒那麼痛苦啦
can reduce the pain when it's being cooked.
# 搞點生薑
Put some ginger.
# 輕輕的塞到它嘴里
I stuff it into the mouth gently.
# 吃了生薑沒那麼腥
It wouldn't smell that fishy after eating the ginger.
# 這樣就很靚啦
And now it's really beautiful.
# 唉 剛好這裡還有一個笋
Eh? I just see a bamboo shoot here.
# 把這個笋也放下去
Why don't we put it in as well?
# 處理下這個笋
Let me tackle it first.
# 這個笋太嫩啦
This bamboo shoot is simply too tender.
# 就那麼一點點
Just a tiny little bit remains.
# 把這個也削下去
I'll slice it,
# 一起煮掉
and cook it together with the fish.
# 你看 把這些笋
Look! The bamboo shoot,
# 削成薄薄的片
I cut it into thin slices.
# 增加它的香味
This can enhance the aroma.
# 把這些配料 要全部塞到肚子上去
The side ingredients, are all to be stuffed into the belly.
# 不然一烤 這個全部都會燒焦的
Otherwise it would all be burnt, once they're grilled.
# 它(吃)得很飽啦
It has eaten a lot.
# 把它裏起來
Let me, wrap it up.
# 哎喲 肚子夠大哦
Ayo! The belly becomes that big,
# 吃了那麼多東西
after eating so many things.
# 還是一條魚
It's still a fish.
# 還是一條魚樣
It still looks like a fish.
# 這是尾巴這裡
This is its tail here.
# 尾巴這裡要多裏一點
The tail here needs to be wrapped a few more times.
# 啊
Ah!
# 等一下我們就直接
Then we can grill it,
# 上烤架
on the stand,
# 燒它
right away.
# 這尾巴歪了一點
The tails is a bit twisted.
# 把它擺正一點
Let me fix it.
# 可以
Okay!
# 我去把那個炭生起來
I'm gonna light up the charcoal.
# 可以喲 炭烤活魚
Nice! Charcoal grilled fish
# 把這個架子放上去 把魚
Put the net on top, and the fish...
# 唉 怎麼不夠長啊
Eh? Why isn't it long enough?
# 尾巴彎一下
Let me bend its tail.
# 這樣烤
Then grill it,
# 這樣現烤著 (註︰下明白想說甚麼)
grill it now.
# 你看這個 這個火生很好旺哦'
Look! The, the fire is really strong, isn't it?
# 聽那 嗶哩啪啦 嗶哩啪啦
Listen! It's like, bila bila.
# 嗯 有點味道出來啦
Um! I can already smell something.
# 你看 這冒煙 (註︰這兩句的原字幕時間出錯)
Look! The steam is coming out.
# 馬上就快好啦
It will be ready very soon.
# 再烤幾個分鐘
Just a few more minutes.
# 就直接拿下去吃啦
Then we can bring it down, and enjoy it right away.
# 唉 唉 這個不燙 你看
Ay! Ay! It's not hot here. Look!
# 好香呀 應該熟啦 下去
It smells really nice! It should be alright now. Let's go downstairs,
# 下去把它刨開來
and open it.
# 應該這樣搓爛
I think I should break it here,
# 把它掰開就可以啦
and then peel it open, and that's it.
# 哎呀 全熟啦
Aya! It's alright now.
# 哎呀
Aya!
# 這肉看上去就好吃
The meat looks very tasty.
# 哇 一整條魚
Wa! The whole fish...
# 你看 整條魚還是原樣的
Look! The whole fish is till in its shape.
# 我來吃一下你的肉 看一下好不好吃
Let me taste your meat, and see if it tastes good.
# 嗯
Um!
# 可以喲
Not bad!
# 好燙
Very hot!
# 你看這個肚子
Have a look at the belly!
# 哎呀
Aya!
# 這個魚泡
This is the swim bladder,
# 就是魚泡哦
swim bladder, you know.
# 好燙
Very hot!
# 這個魚好吃
This fish is really tasty.
# 哇 這竹笋
Wa! The bamboo shoot...
# 可以
Not bad!
# 味道很不錯 這個竹笋
It tastes not bad, the bamboo shoot.
# 沒有辣椒粉 有辣椒粉 加點辣椒粉 味道很不錯的
I don't have any chilli powder. It would taste really nice with some chilli powder.
# 這個等一下留著晚上 晚飯來吃
I'll leave it for the dinner, for the dinner tonight.
# 不然晚上都沒菜吃
We'll have nothing for dinner otherwise.
# 晚上吃米糠拌飯就行啦 這個魚不好吃的
No worries. You'll have rice and bran tonight. The fish doesn't taste good at all.
# 知不知道
Got it?
# 快點 散啦 散啦 散啦 (註︰原字幕少了一次「散啦」)
C'mon! Dismiss, dismiss, dismiss, dismiss!
# 沒甚麼好吃的
It doesn't taste good at all.